玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
In the beginning there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
And then... BANG!
诞生了无限膨胀的
Giving birth to an endless expanding existence
时间 空间和物质
of time, space and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now see further than we've ever imagined,
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence,
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call... THE UNIVERSE
至今和我们的幸存相关 神秘兮兮的 我们最近的邻居
Our closest neighbor, mysterious as it is, tied to our very survival.
自有人类开始它那亮度就一直迷惑着我们
Its luminance has captivated us since the beginning of humanity,
靠近一看揭示出一个永存的神话 争议和谜团之源
but a closer look reveals an ever-present source of myth, controversy and mystery.
无形的力量每天分分秒秒地拉着地球
An unseen force that pulls at the Earth every second of the day,
幻觉与奇景的源头
a source of illusion and wonder,
一个如此靠近人类之家的天体
a celestial body so close to home
它有可能影响到我们的行为方式和我们的身体功能
that it may impact the way we behave and the way our body functions.
若没有月球则我们所熟知的行星地球
And without it, some argue the planet Earth as we know it,
可能永远不可能进化
may never have evolved.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第三集 月球之谜
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 03of19 Mysteries.of.the.Moon
距离地球约24万英里
Almost 240,000 miles from Earth,
在夜空中 我们的月球亮度胜过其它的天体
our Moon outshines every other celestial body in the night sky.
月亮… 当它升起带来光明时
The Moon, when it's up and when it's bright,
使我们产生梦想和惊叹
makes us dream and wonder.
我们神秘的近邻也带来了无数
Our enigmatic neighbor is also the source of
悬而未决的谜团和历史悠久的神话
countless unsolved mysteries and age-old myths.
月球是个怪异的地方
The Moon is a spooky place.
从人类的角度来看这是个神秘的地方
It's a mysterious place from the human perspective.
月球看上去美丽而平淡
the Moon is a beautiful and a really obvious thing to see.
我们难以忽略这个天空中明亮的大球
It's hard to miss, the big shining Moon in the sky.
因此我想所有的人
So, I think all people
一直在努力了解它
from all times have had some need to understand it,
努力适应它
some need to relate to it.
科学会就宇宙的问题投射一束
Science may cast an
观察之光在某些物体上
empirical light on some things about the universe,
然而月球专家在提起月球时
But lunar experts are the first to admit
首先会承认他们没有解决所有的问题
they don't have all the answers when it comes to our Moon.
科学是个过程
Science is about process,
我们从来没有确切的解释
we're never sure about explanation.
我们对月球了解得很少
We know so little about the Moon
那是因为我们近距离观察它才
because we've only been observing it close up
几百年的时间
for a few hundred years,
而它的存在已经超过四 五十亿年了
and it's been there for over 4,5 billion years.
我们的月球在三到四亿年前
Our Moon teemed with volcanic activity
到处都是火山活动
three to four billion years ago.
如今大多数人认为它是个
Today, most believe it's an
漂浮在太空中的死寂之地
inactive dead world floating through space,
然而是这样吗？
but is it?
1969年7月20日
July 20th, 1969.
尼尔·阿姆斯特朗在第一次探访月球表面时
Neil Armstrong took his historic small step
迈出了他历史性的一小步
during that first visit to the lunar surface.
这是个人的一小步
That's one small step for man,
却是人类一个巨大的跨越
one giant leap for mankind.
在月球上
While on the Moon,
阿姆斯特朗报告了看到的东西 他称有个区域
Armstrong reported seeing what he called an area
要比周围的区域
that is considerably more illuminated
明亮得多
than the surrounding area,
那个区域好象
and that the area seems to
有一点点荧光
have a slight amount of fluorescence to it.
那表示什么意思呢？
What could it mean?
近40年后的今天
Today, almost 40 years later,
没有人确切地知道那光源究竟是什么
no one knows exactly what that light source was.
但是科学家曾经目睹过类似的情形
But scientists have witnessed similar occurrences.
月球上的整个等级的变化
There been a whole class of changes on the Moon
已经涉及到明亮
that have involved brightenings,
颜色的变化 甚至气体排放
color changes, and even gaseous emissions.
这些项目已经留给了美国航天局的
These events have left some like NASA
天文学家邦妮·布拉蒂那些人
astronomer Bonnie Buratti,
称之为
perplexed by what they call
"月球瞬变现象"(LTP)的疑惑
"Lunar Transient Phenomena", or LTPs.
月球瞬变现象存在着争议
Lunar Transient Phenomena are controversial.
科学家很持怀疑态度
Scientists are very skeptical about them.
问题是对这些现象没有
The problem is there's no observations,
真正牢靠的观察
true and firm, on these events.
然而从中世纪开始
But ever since the Middle Ages,
月球观察家已经报告看到了那些神秘之光
lunar observers have reported seeing these mysterious lights.
通常被看到
They're usually witnessed
处在月球阴暗模糊的区域里
in the dark shadowy areas of the Moon,
那里对照更加强烈
where the contrast is greater.
它们会随机持续几秒
They last anywhere from a few seconds
到几个小时
to a few hours,
那就是它们很难确认的原因
and that's why they've been so hard to confirm.
肯定了那些谜一般的表现
Convinced that these ethereal displays
是真实的现象
are a real phenomenon,
但是不能确定究竟是什么造成的确
but unsure as to what's causing them,
专家们已经
experts have honed
深入研究几个可能的解释
in on several possible explanations.
对于月球瞬变现象 已经有一些理论
There have been a number of theories that have surfaced
浮出水面
for Lunar Transient Phenomena.
地球上不断变化的视角可能造成了
Ever-changing views from Earth may be causing the appearance
月球上光亮闪烁 变化的现象
of bright flashes or surface changes on the Moon.
某些现象我认为显然只是由于
Some of the events that I've seen are clearly just due to turbulence
地球大气的扰动
in the Earth's atmosphere.
扰动造成了月球的移动和变化
These cause movement and change on the Moon.
但是布拉蒂认为不是所有的月球瞬变现象
But Buratti thinks that not all LTPs
都能用大气扰动来解释
can be explained by atmospheric turbulence.
尼尔·阿姆斯特朗所报告的现象
The anomalies that Neil Armstrong reported
是在月球表面看到的
were seen from the lunar surface,
所以大气扰动不可能造成这种现象
so atmospheric turbulence couldn't be causing them.
许多天文学家
Many astronomers
像格利菲斯天文台的劳拉·丹利
like Laura Danly at the Griffith Observatory,
认为流星和小行星的高速作用
believe that the high-velocity impact of meteors and asteroids
解释了地球上所观察到的这个现象的主要原因
accounts for much of this activity being observed from Earth.
它们移动得非常得快
They're traveling very fast,
所以当它们轰击月球时
so when they smash into the Moon...
确实是一个猛烈明亮的爆炸
There's a big, bright explosion, really.
这些碰撞爆炸被认为是火球
These impact explosions, known as fireballs,
可能是那现象的一个原因
may be one source of the activity,
但是前提是存在一个漏洞
But that premise has a gaping hole in it.
即使我们已经看到了
Even though we've seen
月球阴暗面的那些闪烁
these flashes on the dark side of the Moon,
我们还是没有确定与之相联系的陨石坑
we haven't identified a crater associated with any of them.
这就让我们陷入了争议
And that's where we get into the controversy.
没有任何大的事件
There hasn't been any large event
被确切地观察到
that has been unequivocally observed.
另一个可能的解释是
Another possible explanation
当流星击中月球时
is that when a meteor hits the Moon,
形成了巨大的陨石坑
it creates a massive crater.
围绕着陨石坑边缘的山
Landslides around the crater
崩抬起了月球尘埃的山体
rim kick up mountains of lunar dust.
纤细的尘埃会吸收和散射光线
The fine dust could absorb and scatter light rays
或呈现出好象月球
or make it appear as if the Moon has
某种程度改变了表面特征
somehow changed its surface features.
有可能一旦
It's possible that if
月球表面发生山崩
a landslide occurred on the Moon,
你就会在地球上看到某种现象
you would see something from the Earth,
陨石坑边缘被遮掩了
the edge of a crater being obscured,
形成云状的现象
a cloud-like feature forming.
换句话说我们将看到陨石坑壁
In other words, we would see a crater wall,
那是月球瞬变现象 接着陨石坑壁垮塌了
an LTP, and then a collapsed crater wall.
我们一直没有看到过
We've never seen that yet.
或许在那些月球异常
Perhaps the most controversial
现象背后最具争议的争议
theory behind these lunar anomalies
将改变我们对月球的整个看法
could alter our view of the Moon entirely.
它将挑战信念 即月球已经停止地质活动有几千年了
It would challenge the belief that the Moon has been geologically inactive for millennia.
其中一个对月球瞬变现象
One of the most intriguing explanations
最耐人寻味的解释
for lunar transient phenomena
是月球上有活火山
is active volcanoes on the Moon.
这是最科学的重要理论
This is the most scientifically important
因为它将告诉我们
because it would tell us that
月球的地质仍然是活跃的
the Moon is still geologically active.
阿波罗太空任务期间所拍摄的照片
Photographs taken during the Apollo space missions
揭示了形成于月球表面的岩石
revealed a rocky formation on the lunar surface
是所谓的"非结构的"(inastructure)
called the "inastructure."
对于这个资料科学家推测
With this data, scientists speculated
月球可能经历火山活动
that the Moon could have experienced volcanic activity
是在过去的数百万年前
in the last million years.
这个信息具有突破性
The information was groundbreaking and
它意味着火山活动
it meant that volcanic activity
可能是月球瞬变现象主要起因
could be the primary source of LTPs,
但是大多数科学家尚存疑虑
but most scientists are yet to be convinced.
在科学上
The thing about science is
每当你有了一个理论或者模型
whenever you have a theory or a model,
你必须能够获取其结果的数据
you have to be able to get data of an event
一遍又一遍
over and over again.
在那些更加神秘的增亮
In terms of these more mysterious brightenings
或有可能是火山活动的情况方面
or things that could be volcanic events,
实际上我们从来没有两个独立的观察者
we've never actually had two independent observers
在同一时刻获得无可争辩的数据
obtain incontrovertible data at the same time.
即使月球上没有地质活动
Even if the Moon isn't geologically active,
有些天文学家认为 可能会有气体
some astronomers believe there may be gases left over
在当时火山活动频繁时残留了下来
from a time when the volcanic activity was prevalent.
如果残留的气体到达表面
If residual gases reach the surface,
太阳光会散射出
the Sun's rays would scatter
气体粒子红与蓝的色彩
colored hues of red and blue from the gas particles.
月球仍然可能在经历着
The Moon could still be experiencing
排气而内部实际上没有活动
outgassing without having actual activity in the interior.
月球里的矿物产生着气体
There are minerals in the Moon that produce gases, and they seep up
它们渗透出月球的表面
to the surface in the Moon and come out.
有这么多的月球瞬变现象理论摆在面前
With so many lunar transient phenomena theories out there,
哪一个是最合理的呢？
which is the most plausible?
布拉蒂博士没有明确哪一个
Dr. Buratti doesn't point to one
适合于现象
explanation for the phenomenon.
我认为月球瞬变现象的原因可能有无数个
I think the reasons for LTP are probably myriad.
我认为存在不止一个的解释
I think there's more than one explanation.
它不只是一种现象
It's not just one phenomenon,
可能是许多不同类型的活动
it's many different types of activities.
目前 难以捉摸的
For now, the cause of the elusive
月球瞬变现象的起因
lunar transient phenomena
可能继续隐藏在月球的阴暗面
may remain hidden on the dark side of the Moon.
然而满月导致地球上狂热的起因
But the cause of full Moon fever here on Earth
诊断起来甚至更加棘手
may be even tougher to diagnose.
如果有的话那满月对我们的身心
What role, if any,
究竟有什么作用？
does the full Moon have on our bodies and our minds?
当提到探究月球之谜时
When it comes to exploring the mysteries of the Moon,
也许最著名和最具争议的是
perhaps the most celebrated and controversial
我们的卫星是否对身心有什么影响
is whether our satellite has any influence on the mind and body.
我们知道地球与月球之间存在某种关系
We know that there's some relationship between the Earth and the Moon,
因此或许不是明显地突现 在想象中
and so, it's perhaps not such a great leap to imagine that
有不同的变化
the different changes
满月可能会对人产生某种影响
the full Moon might have some influence on people.
存在着许多许多的奥秘… 如身体上的
There are lots and lots of mysteries, physical
和心理上的
and psychological.
有一个词形容疯狂 "精神失常(lunacy)"
One of the words for madness, "lunacy, "
它源于拉丁语的月亮 "luna"
comes from the Latin word for Moon, "luna."
所以我认为贯穿历史
So i think throughout history,
人们已经将月亮与人的心理联系在了一起
people have associated the Moon with human psychology.
很多人真的相信满月影响到他们的行为
A lot of people really believe that the full Moon affects
也许影响到他们的生物化学或类似的东西
their behavior, affects maybe their biochemistry or something like that.
许多人广泛地坚信
There's a widely held belief
其中包括临床医生
among many people including clinicians
在满月的时候
that during a full Moon,
急诊室候诊有变化 明显的变化
there are changes, palpable changes in emergency room visits,
在怀孕率
in pregnancy rates,
出生率方面
in birthrates.
有一个神话说的是
There is a mythology about behavior
行为举止随着月相而变化
which changes consistently with the phases of the Moon.
轶事证据比比皆是 但科学是否支持那信念
Anecdotal evidence abounds, but does science support the belief
即满月对地球的居住者有没有明显的的作用呢？
that a full Moon has a measurable effect on the Earth's occupants?
人们早就试图将月球
People have long tried to associate
及月球的引力作用与人和动物的行为联系起来
the Moon, and the gravitational effects of the Moon with behavior in people and animals.
事实是 月球搅动着
Fact: the Moon stirs up the oceans
占我们星球七成面积的海洋
which make up 70 percent of our planet.
因此如果我们的身体是由70%的水组成的话
So if the human body is made up of 70 percent water,
那不会意味着月亮也同样在拉扯着
wouldn't that mean the Moon has just as much pull
我们人体呢？
on human beings?
一些医学界德高望重的成员
some respected members of the medical community
已有报告 在满月时人的行为方面
have reported changes in human behavior
及生理学上的变化
and physiology during full Moons.
我们必须无偏见地得到关注
We must be open minded
作为仔细观察者
and as careful observers,
继续假设某种关系联系着
continue to posit some relationship
月相变化与
between changes in the lunar cycle
我们的行为举止
and the way in which we behave,
我们的健康与疾病模型建立在时间的前面
the way in which our health and disease patterns move ahead through time,
那么我们或许就需要提出一个
then we probably need to ask
创造性的 批判性的 严谨的问题  这有可能吗？
in creative and critical and rigorous fashion,the question, "is this possible?"
在执法部门有些人
There are some in law enforcement
认为犯罪率会上升
who believe the crime rates increase
在满月时
when the Moon is full.
但是第一线的其他人可不这么认为
But others manning the front lines aren't so sure.
是的 这种说法
Well, the way i see it,
在我个人看来像是个神话
personally, I see it as a myth.
在满月开始变化之时
At the start of a full Moon shift, deputy Jose Castro,
副主管约瑟·卡斯特罗供职于西好莱坞的司法部门
with the west Hollywood sheriff's department,
嘲笑那月球与人扯上关系的说法
scoffed at the idea that a lunar pull has any effect on people.
然而在他当值的头20分钟里
But in his first 20 minutes on duty,
已经有三通呼叫进来了
three calls had already come in.
眼下我们正在响应488
Right now we're responding to a 488,
这是刚刚发生的盗窃案
which is a theft that had just occurred.
呼叫称是个男人 讲西班牙语
The call indicates that
大约32岁 身穿橙色监狱服装
a male, Hispanic, approximately 32 years of age, wearing an orange jail jumpsuit,
没穿裤子
no pants,
蓝色的衬衣
wearing blue underwear,
偷了一本书
stole a book.
眼下我们正在响应273.5的呼叫
Right now we're responding to a call of the 273.5,
那是个现在正在发生的家庭暴力
which is a domestic violence now that is happening.
这是一段时期以来第一例家庭暴力
This is the first domestic violence we've had in a while
它只是刚巧发生在满月
and it just so happens there is a full Moon.
现在我们正在去某个名流的途中
Right now we are en route to a certain celebrity
他就住在我们的区域内
that lives within our area.
向名流的家投掷瓶子
The call states that a neighbor at this...celebrity's residence is throwing bottles
在报案者的前院
at the informant's front yard.
截止到一年中最繁忙的周二夜晚
By the end of his busiest Tuesday night of the year,
副主管卡斯特罗的怀疑正开始减退
deputy Castro's skepticism was beginning to wane.
现在我来说给你听
Now, I'll tell you what.
在开始转变的那一刻我还是不大相信
At the beginning of the shift, I wasn't a big believer.
但是现在我成了信徒
But I'm becoming a believer now.
这有许多是联系
A lot of this is tied to the idea
到月球引起地球上潮汐
that the Moon causes tides on Earth
那么有可能会引起人体内的潮汐
so maybe it causes tides within people,
但那是不可能发生的
but that just can't happen.
月亮对我们的身体是不会有潮汐作用的
The Moon does not have a tidal effect on our bodies.
我的胸部没有因为月亮在拉扯而大起来
My chest doesn't get bigger because the Moon is pulling on it.
彼得·普雷斯曼医生
Dr. Peter Pressman,
洛杉矶的西德斯西奈医学中心的一名医生
a medical doctor at Cedars-Sinai Hospital in Los Angeles,
承认自己的一些同行
acknowledged that some of his peers
相信月球影响到人的行为
believe that the Moon influences human behavior.
医生们相信
Physicians who believe
月球确实影响到我们的身体和行为
that...the Moon does affect our bodies and our behavior,
得出的结论是建立在他们观察的基础上的
come to that conclusion on the basis of their observations.
这些观察结果可能会遭到歪曲
And those observations may be very skewed.
它们可能是场合性的
They may be very situational
可能并不能说明什么
and they may not mean a thing,
除非有人作为研究对象了
except that that's what somebody has observed.
但是普雷斯曼怀疑那断言可能包含着偏见
But Pressman suspects the claims may contain a bias
基于个人经验的基础上的偏见
that's based on personal experiences.
如果你留意证据 你会发现
If you look at the evidence, you find
真的没有明确的机制
that there really is no clear mechanism
来说明月球的影响
for the influence of the Moon
与人体健康与疾病的关系
with health and disease in human beings.
不过 还是继续有精明的医生
Nevertheless, there continue to be astute clinicians
作为仔细的观察家在坚持
and careful observers who insist
自己看到了那关系
that they do see relationships.
驱使人们行为的是他们所相信的东西
People's behavior is driven by what they believe
如果你相信月球有一些神奇之处
and if you believe there is something magical about the Moon
它掌握着对你的魔咒的话 那么或许你就会改变自己的行为
and it holds a spell over you then perhaps you will change your behavior.
不管满月是否
Whether the full Moon
对身心具有明显的影响
has any measurable impact on body and mind,
都将继续是争论的起因
will continue to be a source of debate
和我们月亮神话的一部分
and part of the mythology of our Moon.
围绕着我们最近的邻居
And there are other mythological legends
还有其它神话传说
surrounding our closest neighbor.
尽管那样不是每个人都能够看到
Even then, not everyone can see
月球上的"人"
the man in the Moon.
是那些巨大的暗的区域
The man on the Moon are these giant dark
创作出来的 有些人认为看上去像
areas that create what some people think looks like
眼球 鼻子和笑脸
eyeballs and a nose, and smiley face.
我先表明
Let me begin by saying
我从来没有见到过月球上的人
that I have never seen the man on the Moon.
人们怎样才能看到它
And how anyone can see it
关键在于主观创造性
is a matter of...subjective creativity.
月亮长期以来一直就是传说和神话的对象
The Moon has long been the object of lore and myth.
但是我们认为我们所看到的全部
But what we think we see is all
是观看者眼中的东西
in the eye of the beholder.
多数文化其实并没有看到月球上的人
Most cultures actually don't see a man on the Moon.
兔子是许多人的宠物
The rabbit is a big favorite among many
还有其它的东西
and there are others.
然而大家举头望月
But everyone who looks up at the Moon,
可以看到月球表面的明亮 昏暗的区域
can see light and dark areas on the lunar surface.
这些不是幻觉
And these are not an illusion
而是非常真实的高山和峡谷
but very real mountains and valleys.
明亮的区域是崎岖 多坑的高地
The light areas are rugged, cratered highlands
叫做"terrae" 拉丁语的"土地"
known as, "terrae," Latin for "lands".
高地是月球原始地壳的一部分
The highlands are part of the Moon's original crust
遭受到流星
that was shattered by the impact of meteoroids,
小行星 彗星的冲击破坏
asteroids, and comets.
月球上昏暗的区域叫做"maria"
The darker areas on the Moon are known as "maria".
"Maria"的意思是"海"
"Mare" is a word meaning "sea".
那是远古的熔岩
They are ancient lava beds that were
从前是流动的 但现在已经凝固了
at one time flowing, but are now solid.
形成于几十亿年前的火山喷发影响
Formed from impact cratering over billions of years,
月海的面积占了月球表面的16%
the maria account for 16 percent of the Moon surface
看上去像水体
and look like bodies of water.
最新的看法是有巨大的小行星
The latest thinking is that giant asteroids
击中了月球的另外一面
hit the other side of the Moon
震撼着月球非常地醒目
and rocked the Moon so significantly
熔岩在我们所看到的这一面渗透出来
that lava oozed out of the side that we see
形成了这些大片的昏暗的熔岩区域
and created these big dark expanses of lava
当然随着时间推移凝固了
that of course, solidified over time.
形成明暗对比的
The ancient volcanic activity
远古火山活动
that formed the contrasts of dark and light
被无意的中创造出 看上去
have inadvertently created what some see
像是人面特征
as the features of a human face.
眼球实际上是雨海(Mare Imbrium)
The eyeballs are actually the Mare Imbrium,
和静海(Mare Serenitatis)
sea of rains
意思是宁静之海
and the Mare Serenitatis which means sea of serenity.
鼻子是暑湾(Sinus Aestuum) 意思是巨浪之湾
The nose is the Sinus Aestuum, which means bay of billows.
大嘴是云海(Mare Nubium)
And the open mouth is the Mare Nubium,
和认知海(Mare Cognitum)
the sea of clouds and the Mare Cognitum,or sea of knowledge.
人们看到月球上的"人"
For humans to see a man on the Moon
可能是源于我们试图了解月球奥秘
may be our way of trying to understand the lunar mystery
以及我们与之不可分割联系在一起的缘故
and how we're inextricably connected to it.
许多月球之谜
Many mysteries of the Moon
已经深刻地影响到了我们的文明
have influenced our civilization in dramatic ways.
古人将历法
Ancient man based his calendar,
农业 数学以及天文学
agriculture, mathematics,
建立在不断交替但始终一贯的月相上
and astronomy...on the changing but consistent phases of the Moon.
在每个月里月球表现出在8个
Every month, the Moon appears to change its shape
月相循环周期上变化
during an eight phase spin cycle.
为什么月球会有月相？
Why does the Moon have phases?
月相的发生是因为
The phases of the Moon
月球围绕着地球旋转
occur because as the Moon orbits around the Earth,
我们看到的是它明亮一面的圆缺
we see more or less of its lit side.
我们看到的月球反射出来的
The light we see being reflected from the Moon
光实际上是来自太阳
is actually coming from the Sun.
想象一下太阳在这里
Imagine the Sun is over there
这是地球
and this is the Earth
这是月球
and this is the Moon.
当月球被太阳完全照亮时
When the Moon is fully lit by the Sun
我们就能看到它的亮面 那是满月
and we can see that lit side, it's a full Moon.
随着月球围绕着地球运行
As the Moon goes around the Earth,
我们看到亮面越来越小
we see less and less
而暗面越来越大
of the lit side and more and more of the dark side.
满月时月球是在
The full Moon occurs when the Moon is
太阳到地球的对面
on the opposite side of the Earth from the Sun
面对我们的月球表面整个被照亮
and the lunar surface facing us is fully lit.
月相的样子
The shapes of the phases of the Moon
是由于我们在地球上观察的角度
are due to our perspective on Earth,
看到的是月球亮面的多与少
seeing more or less of the lit side of the Moon.
事实不然 比如
It's not a case of...
地球遮挡了一些会照到月球的光
for example, the Earth blocking some of the...light that would have otherwise struck the Moon.
不管怎样确实发生了月食
That does occur, however, during an eclipse.
地球上远看
And that terrestrial perspective
有时会捉弄我们
can sometimes play tricks on us.
当提起月球的大小时
When it comes to the Moon size,
视觉会被蒙骗
looks can be deceiving.
一些月球之谜很难理解
Some of the Moon's mysteries are difficult to comprehend
我们的眼睛告诉我们的是一回事 而科学告诉的则是另一回事
when our eyes tell us one thing and science, another.
我们只是需要对问题不同的视角
We just need a different perspective on the problem.
有时满月在空中升起
Sometimes when the full Moon rises in the sky,
在地平线附近看上去要比
it appears much larger near the horizon
它在空中更高的地方来得大
than it does when it's positioned higher in the sky.
有些观察者判断月球在刚出现时
Some observers judge the Moon to be as much as
要大出50到75%
50 to 75 percent larger when it first appears.
那么满月在地平线附近时真的要大点吗？
but is the full Moon really larger when it's near the horizon?
我的朋友都认为月亮
My friends all think that the Moon is bigger
在地平线上时要更大些
when it's on the horizon.
我认为月亮在地平线上时要更大些
I think that the Moon is bigger when it's on the horizon.
那么是什么原因造成了看上去会如此不同呢？
So what could be causing it to look so different?
月球并没有真正改变它
The Moon doesn't really change its apparent size
从地平线到头顶的外观大小 但我们的视觉却是它要大些
from the horizon to overhead. but our perception is that it's larger.
一种理论认为我们的头脑里判断月亮的大小
One theory is that our mind judges the Moon's size
是与其它的物体有关
in relation to other objects.
在地平线上看上去大些是因为
It looks much larger at the horizon because
存在着我们能够与其相比较的东西
there are things we can compare it to,
而在头顶上时
whereas at the top of the sky,
只是其早已熟悉的自身形象
it's out there by its little old self.
换句话说
In other words,
如果我们看到被月球比下去的 像房子那样大的物体
if we see a large object such as a house dwarfed by the Moon,
我们的大脑里就会告诉我们月球必然非常巨大
our mind tells us that the Moon must be enormous.
然而当月球孤身出现时 我们的大脑就不会作出那样的判断
But when the Moon is out by itself, our mind doesn't make that assumption,
看到的月球就很小
we see the Moon as small.
另一种可能性是庞邹错觉引起的
Another possible cause of this is the Ponzo illusion,
是以马里奥·庞邹的名字命名的
named after Mario Ponzo,
他提出大脑判断一个物体的大小
who suggested that the mind judges the size of an object
是基于它的背景
based on its background.
庞邹画出两条相同的线条
Ponzo drew two identical bars
横跨在随着距离消退的
across a picture of railroad tracks
铁路轨道的图片上
as they recede in the distance.
上面的线条看上去要宽些
The upper bars look wider
那是因为它们看上去跨过了铁轨
because they appear to span the rails,
相对下面的线条恰好在铁轨之间
compared to the lower bars, which fits between the rails.
然而事实上骑跨在铁轨上的线
But in fact, the lines overlaid on the tracks
两端的尺寸是一样的
are the same size at both ends.
带着一支铅笔到户外去 当月亮升起时
Go out and take a pencil, and when the Moon is rising,
拿上铅笔 伸出手臂
put the pencil out at arms length and see how big the Moon is
看月亮相对铅笔上橡皮头有多大 然后几个小时后再出去
compared to the eraser on the pencil, and then go out a couple of hours later
在月亮升得更高时再做一遍
and do the same thing when the Moon is higher in the sky
你就会看到在两个时段里月亮相对铅笔的橡皮头
and you'll see that the Moon is exactly the same size
大小实际上是一样的
in relation to the pencil eraser at both times.
当提起月亮的大小时可能会把我们戏弄一下
The Moon may play tricks with us when it comes to judging its size,
但是它对我们地球的影响可不是虚构的
but there is nothing imaginary about its effects on our Earth.
在所有隐蔽的月球之谜中
Of all the hidden lunar mysteries,
有一个是刚好能够在地球上观察到的
there is one that can be observed right here on Earth.
这可能是能归咎于月球的
It may be the most influential phenomena
最有影响力的现象
that can be attributed to the Moon.
在我们的地球上
From our place on Earth,
潮汐每天有规律地出现
tides just appear to be the times of day when the
其时海水涨落
sea rises and falls.
不过那是个相互作用 引力的相互作用
But that's an interaction, a gravitational interaction,
在月球与地球之间
between the Moon and the Earth,
因此当月球经过时…
so when the Moon is passing by...
它拉动海洋 把它抬起
It pulls on the oceans and pulls it up higher
这时我们看到了一个高潮位
and we see it as a high tide.
海洋潮汐是由
The ocean tides are caused
太阳和月球的引力引起的
by the gravitational pull of the Sun and our Moon.
太阳和月球两者吸引着地球
The Sun and the Moon both pull on the Earth
造成了潮汐
and contribute to tides.
但是月球要近得多
but the Moon is much closer so its pull of gravity
所以它的引力感觉到比太阳更强
is felt more strongly than the Sun's.
海洋学家Tetjana Ross
Oceanographer Tetjana Ross
称月球永恒不变地拽着地球是很可怕的
says the Moon's constant tug on the Earth is formidable.
月球的影响在潮汐中
The reason that the Moon's influence
如此明显的原因
is so visible in the form of tides
是因为水能够…
is because water can...
流动 水是柔性的
run, it can move. it's malleable.
在加拿大一个偏远的海湾里
In a remote bay in Canada,
一个社区已经学会了与神秘极端的
one community has learned to live
海洋潮汐共同生活
with mysterious and extreme ocean tides
这种潮汐是地球上其它地方看不到的
that are found nowhere else on Earth.
虽然普通的潮汐涨起平均是3英尺
While normal tides rise by an average of three feet,
但是在新斯科舍和新不伦瑞克
the waters along the bay of
之间的芬迪湾的海水
Fundy between Nova Scotia and New Brunswick
每天两次涨起50英尺
swell up to 50 feet twice every day.
芬迪湾涨起这么大的潮汐的原因之一
One of the reasons the bay of Fundy has such large tides
是因为海湾下面的地形地貌
is because of the shape of the landforms underneath the bay
它是漏斗形的
it's kind of a funnel shaped,
只要水面抬起 它就迅速升起
and so as the water level rises it really rises rapidly.
高潮来时1000亿吨海水
At high tide, a hundred billion tons of water
在一个小时左右涌进海湾
sloshes into the bay in a matter of hours.
然后在退潮时
Then during low tide,
大部分海水象浴缸一样排出去
most of it drains out like a bathtub.
形成的海湾就是这样
The bay is shaped just so,
所以最先的潮汐来到时
so that the first tide comes in
就象波浪往前推
like a wave and it moves along.
被顶回 来到口子上
reflects off the back and it comes out to the mouth
刚好同时又一拨潮水
just at the same time as the next
赶来了 所以它们叠加了起来 对此我们称之为共振
tide had built up and so they add up in what we call "resonance."
潮汐共振恰好是
Tidal resonance is just getting the...
与高潮升起同时发生的
rise of the high tides to coincide;
某些波长反映出来的是
Certain wavelengths are reflected in a way that
它们相互增强
they reinforce each other
相互放大
and amplify each other
潮汐因此而被加强了
and the tide...is therefore amplified.
芬迪湾独特的漏斗形状
The unique funnel shape of the bay of Fundy
促使了这个共振和推高了潮位
contributes to this resonance and the height of its tides.
海湾逐渐分裂成一系列的
The bay gradually splits into a series of
内港与河叉约束了潮流 促成了奇特的潮汐
basins and river junctions that restricts the tidal flow and contributes to the extraordinary tides.
潮汐是我们星球永远和月球栓在一起的又一种形式
Tides, one more way our planet is forever tied to the Moon.
然而还没有因此结束
But it doesn't end there.
我们知道月球的引力一直在拉扯着
We know that the Moon's gravity is constantly pulling up
我们地球的海洋 同时地球的引里也在拉扯着月球
on the Earth's oceans while the Earth's gravity pulls down on the Moon.
太空中一切物体都在被别的物体拉扯着
Everything in space is tugging on everything else
因此地球拉扯着月球
so the Earth is tugging on the Moon
而月球也拉扯着地球
and the Moon is tugging on the Earth.
月球拉扯我们的海洋是如此的强烈
The Moon's gravitational pull on our oceans is so powerful
造成了我们地球的两边所谓的"潮起"
that it creates what's called a "tidal bulge" on both sides of the planet.
月球吸引着地球的引力
The Moon pulls on the Earth gravitationally and...
一旦这样它也拉扯着海洋
when it does so, it also pulls on the oceans that are sort of
向它稍微有点隆起
stretched up a little bit toward it.
它最先拉起地球的前面
it pulls preferentially on the front side of the Earth,
把海洋拉向它
pushes, pulls the ocean toward it,
然后拉着地球有一点点缩小
then pulls the Earth a little bit less,
而在背面
and in the backside,
海洋拉向月球没那么厉害
the ocean is not pulled quite as far toward the Moon.
所以那就是为什么地球上会有两个
So that's why there are two
所谓的"潮起"
bulges that are called "tidal bulges" on the Earth.
我们辽阔的海洋上的潮汐隆起
Tidal bulges on our vast oceans
实际上影响到了地球的自转
actually impact the Earth's rotation.
潮汐隆起是月球造成的
This tidal bulge that's created by the Moon,
它朝着月球稍微有一点点突出
it's moving out ahead of the Moon a little bit,
月球实际上是往后拉着
and the Moon is actually pulling back
这个潮汐隆起
on this tidal bulge.
那么当月球往后拉着这个潮汐隆起时
Now, when the Moon pulls back on this tidal bulge,
也在减缓地球的旋转
that slows the Earth down.
没有我们的月球 地球将旋转的快得多
Without our Moon, the Earth would spin much faster
我们的一天将会短得多
and our days would be much shorter.
这将影响到这个行星上生命的进化
and this would affect how life has evolved on this planet.
然而这些潮汐的力量
But these tidal forces,
把地球栓在月球上的
which tie the Earth to the Moon,
可是双向作用的
travel a two-way street.
我们地球对月球也具有不可否认的影响
Our Earth also has an undeniable effect on the Moon.
那么如果月球上有水的话
So if the Moon had water on it,
地球的引力也会造成
would the Earth's gravitational pull
月球海洋类似的潮汐吗？
cause similar tides on lunar oceans?
答案是会的
The answer is yes.
事实上几十亿年前
In fact, billions of years ago,
月球上几乎全部是液体
the Moon was almost entirely made up of liquid,
但不是水
but not water.
当月球刚刚诞生 非常年轻时
When the Moon was first formed and very young,
完全是液体的岩石 岩浆
it was entirely liquid rock, magma.
月球曾经一直象天空中炽热的地狱
The Moon would've been like a blazing inferno in the sky.
因为岩石是液体的
And because the rock was liquid,
尽管还是岩石
even though it was rock,
地球拉扯的引力
the gravitational pull of the Earth
以及月球的轨道
and the orbit of the Moon
引起了液体岩石的潮汐
caused the liquid rock to have tides,
就象如今地球上的水
just like the water on the Earth today.
随着时间的推移 月球以及它的熔岩潮汐
Over time, the Moon and its lava tides
冷却形成了固体的荒凉景色
cooled into a solid desolate landscape.
但是地球与月球之间的
But the gravitational relationship
引力关系一直没有结束
between the Earth and the Moon has never ceased.
能够想象每个夜晚
But imagine if there was
没有了月亮露面的情景吗
no Moon making an appearance each night.
世界将会有什么不同呢？
How different a world would it be?
我们总是和这个叫做月球的神秘天体联系在一起
We're always tied to this mysterious orb we call the Moon.
然而一旦没有了月球 地球会有什么结果呢？
But what would have happened to Earth if there were no Moon?
事实上 我们存活到现在部分原因是由于月球
The fact that we exist today is in part, due to the Moon
一直在让地球打造
allowing the Earth to create
我们赖以生存的环境 早期的海洋 所有的矿物
the environment, the early oceans, all the minerals that allow us to exist.
如果从来就没有月球的话 现在的地球将是另外一个模样
If there had never been a Moon, Earth would be a different place today.
因为月球引起了地球上的潮汐
Because the Moon creates tides on Earth
塑造了我们的海岸线 景观
that shape our shorelines and shape the landscape.
这是月球影响我们进化的情形
Here's how the Moon impacted our evolution.
大约4.5亿年前
About 4 1/2 billion years ago,
月球与地球之间的引力要比现在强好多好多
the gravitational forces between the Moon and Earth were much stronger.
当时月球已经形成 它距离地球要比现在近好多好多
When the Moon was formed, it was much, much closer to us than it is today.
它围绕地球旋转一周仅仅5个小时
It took only five hours for it to orbit the Earth.
由于它离得太近所以它在空中非常庞大
And it was huge in the sky because it was so much closer.
月球施加给地球的很强的引力
And more gravity exerted onto the Earth from a closer Moon
意味着世界对我们的命运来说犹如一个物种
meant the world to our fate as a species.
在很近的月球的影响下 海洋第一次冲刷我们的星球时
When oceans first washed our planet under a closer Moon,
潮汐是今天的1000倍大
the tides were a thousand times greater than they are today.
你能想象得出
And you could imagine
不是我们现在看到的10英尺的潮汐
that instead of having a 10-foot tide like we have today,
而是1万英尺的潮汐
you'd have a 10,000-foot tide.
因此你就有了1万英尺的潮汐所冲刷的内陆了
So, you would have 10,000-foot tides rushing inland.
这些猛烈的潮汐有助于创造出适宜的
These intense tides helped create the right
海洋环境让生命得以发育
conditions in the oceans for life to develop.
潮汐撕开了地壳坚硬的外层
Tides ripped the outer layers of the crust
卷入了大海
off of the Earth, and put them into the oceans.
矿产丰富的汤汁 原始的汤汁
And that mineral-rich soup, the primordial soup,
能够培育和进化生命
was capable of developing and evolving life.
有些科学家认为潮水坑将是生命进化
And some scientists believe that tidal pools would have been an ideal setting
和适应陆地环境的理想之地
for life to evolve and adapt to a terrestrial environment.
那将是个了不起的地方
That would have been a great place,
比如对于来自海洋的第一批生物长出自己的腿
for example, for the first...creatures from the sea to get their legs.
它们可以来到潮水坑里
They could have come into a tidal pool where
那里干半天 湿半天
it's wet half the day and dry half the day,
将是个非常棒的地方 能够长出你的腿
and it would have been a great place to grow your legs
并最终走向陆地
and eventually move onto land.
按照天文学家尼尔·科明斯的说法
According to astronomer Neil Comins,
我们不能低估月球对我们作为一个物种进化的影响
we can't underestimate the Moon's influence on our development as a species.
若没有月球我不认为进化的过程
Without the Moon, I don't think that that process
会如此的快
would have occurred nearly as quickly.
我们已经进化到我们的生物钟
We have evolved so that our biological clocks
基于了大约23到24小时了
are based on around 23, 24-hour time.
如果月球从来没有过
If the Moon had never existed,
那么一天就将是6小时长
the day would be six hours long,
我们作为生物是没法生存到现在的
and we, as the creatures we are today, couldn't exist.
随着月球减缓了地球的运行 稳定了我们的旋转
As the Moon slowed Earth's orbit, it stabilized our rotation
影响到我们的气候和海洋潮汐
and affected our climate and ocean tides.
月球极大地影响了哺乳动物的进化
And the Moon greatly influenced the development of mammals
所以它们的生存依赖于月光之夜
so dependent on Moonlit nights for their survival.
月球对我们的生存确实产生了重大的影响了吗？
Has the Moon had a major impact on our existence?
我想 绝对是的
I think absolutely.
每次月圆时
Every time the Moon is full,
月球的模样是一模一样的
the lunar image is exactly the same.
这是个令人费解之谜
There's a puzzling mystery to this.
它让许多人感到困惑
It makes many wonder
我们为什么永远看不到月球的另外一面
why we never see another side of the Moon.
经过了45亿年的演变
After 4.5 billion years of evolving,
地月系统已经到达了这一点
the Earth-Moon system has arrived at a point
月球始终将同一个面露给我们看
where the Moon shows us the same face all the time.
几十亿年前
Billions of years ago,
火山潮汐所引起的摩擦
the friction created by volcanic tides
造成了月球减缓了自己的旋转
caused the Moon to slow its rotation
成为了对地球潮汐锁定了
and become tidally locked to Earth.
这并不意味我们的月球不在旋转
This doesn't mean our Moon isn't spinning,
而是在几十亿年后
But it has slowed down
转的缓慢了
considerably over billions of years.
月球的秘密要隐藏在另外一面
And the secret of the Moon's hidden far side
就必须保持同步
has to do with synchronicity.
如果这是地球
If this is the Earth
这是我们所看到的月球的那一面
and if this is the side of the Moon that we see,
如果月球不在旋转的话
if the Moon were not rotating,
那么 最终我们会看到月球的另外一面的
then, eventually, we would see the other side of the Moon.
因为月球旋转的速度
Because the Moon is rotating
与它围绕地球旋转的速度相同
at the same rate that it orbits the Earth,
同步旋转 所以我们就始终看到同一个面
synchronous rotation, we always see the same side.
月球的另外一面不总是黑暗的
The far side of the Moon is not always dark.
如果到太空中你就能看到
If you were out in space, you'd be able to see that
太阳照射到月球的所有的面
the Sun hits all sides of the Moon
伴随着月球围绕地球一个月长的轨道运行
as the Moon makes its month-long orbit around the Earth.
然而在我们所处的地方 我们就只能看到一个面
But from where we sit, we can only see one side.
引力牢牢控制着地月关系
Gravity is in firm control of the Earth-Moon relationship.
对吗？
Or is it?
把月球掌控在我们轨道上的
The gravity that has held the Moon in our orbit
引力正慢慢地失去控制…
is slowly losing its grip...
其后果是
and the consequences of
足以让人看到月球
that are enough to make one look at the Moon
发出全新的月光
in a whole new light.
引力是地球抓住月球的力
Gravity is the force that holds the Moon to the Earth.
正像运动员拉住… 链球
Just as this athlete is bound to the...hammer
围绕着自己的身体旋转
that is orbiting about his body,
因此引力将月球与地球栓在一起
so gravity binds the Moon and the Earth.
如果引力突然消失了
if gravity all of a sudden went away,
那么月球就将飞到太空中去了
the Moon would fly off into space,
就象这个链球飞出场地一样
just as this hammer flies off over the field.
当然 引力的作用永远不会终止的
Of course, gravity never stops working.
然而月球会以某种方式悄悄挣脱对其的控制吗？
but could the Moon somehow slip loose of its grip?
事实是月球一直在慢慢地游离我们
The truth is the Moon has always been slowly slipping away from us.
月球一直在不停地远离 而且它还在远离
The Moon has been moving away, and it's still moving away.
事实上月球远离我们的速度
In fact, the Moon moves away from us
是每年两英寸
a couple of inches every year.
最后 月球将远离到
And eventually, the Moon is gonna be so far away
不像我们现在所见到的月球
that it won't even seem like our Moon anymore.
打月球与地球相互交织在一起以来
Ever since the Moon and Earth became intertwined,
地球引力拽拉的能量
the energy from the Earth's gravitational tug
一直在引起月球螺旋着逐渐远离我们的星球
has been causing the Moon to spiral away from our planet.
它目前正远离我们
It's currently moving away from us
以每年一到两英寸的速度
at a rate of one to two inches each year.
这个意想不到的影响的关键
The key to this unexpected effect
在于由月球造成地球的潮汐隆起
are the tidal bulges created on the Earth by the Moon.
地球上的潮汐实际上是在
The tides on Earth actually act to
把月球推出去 每次绕地球运行都在旋转着 一步步远离地球
to propel the Moon outward, spiraling out further from the Earth every orbit.
原因是地球的自转要比月球
The reason is because the Earth spins faster
围绕我们旋转来得快
than the Moon orbits us. So...
所以在月球拉起一个潮汐隆起
after the Moon has pulled up a tidal bulge,
造成高潮位后
raised the high tide,
地球的旋转和拉动稍微比它有点提前
the Earth turns and pulls slightly ahead of it.
所以 就有那么一点点向前的力
So, there's just a little bit of a forward
我们称之为扭矩 有那么一点点额外的
force, we call it a torque, a little bit of an extra kick
非常细微的加速的反冲力
that speeds it up ever so slightly,
然而随着时间的推移 不停的加速使得它跑得越来越快
but over time, that speeding up makes it go faster and faster, which,
在轨道上 就意味着它不停地旋转着 走得越来越远
in orbit, means it's going, spiraling further and further away.
随着时间的推移 月球将扩大自己的轨道
Over time the Moon will expand its orbit
直到有那么一天 最终超出我们地球的引力范围
until someday it will finally be beyond our Earth's gravity.
但是科学家称没有理由为此恐慌
But scientists say there is no cause for panic.
还要经过相当长的时间后
Quite a bit of time will pass before
月球会走出我们的视野 脱离轨道
the Moon is out of sight and out of orbit.
估计最终的离开
Estimated time of total departure,
将要500亿年的时间
about 50 billion years.
而我们的太阳继续燃烧将不足100亿年
And our Sun will flame out in less than 10 billion years.
纵贯历史月球给我们带来了欣喜
Throughout history, the Moon has delighted,
惊奇 有时还有恐慌
surprised, and sometimes terrified us.
我们地球的运动
And the movement of our Earth
可能是月球之谜的起因
may be the cause of this mystery.
月球的另外一个秘密
Another secret of the Moon
已经被记载到了古代的文献中了
has been documented in ancient texts
并一直为之震惊
and continues to amaze.
它通常每隔几年就会出现
it usually appears every few years.
在月全食期间 整个月球会戏剧性地改变颜色
During a total lunar eclipse, the full Moon dramatically changes colors.
究竟是什么原因呢？
What causes this?
月食的道理很简单
A lunar eclipse is very simple.
它只是当地球走到
It just occurs
太阳与月球中间时才发生的
when the Earth gets between the Sun and the Moon.
所以当地球遮挡时
So when Earth gets in the way,
地球投下一个巨大的阴影
Earth casts a giant shadow...
阻挡了阳光照射到月球上
that blocks the sunlight from reaching the Moon.
在月食的食甚时
At the peak of this eclipse,
月球完全进入到了地球的阴影即本影时颜色转变
the Moon passes completely into Earth's shadow or umbra,
并不是人们所预料的全黑
and transforms, not to black,
而是变成了血红色
as one might expect, but to a blood red.
结果是一些
What happens is some of the sunlight
被地球阻挡的阳光
that's being blocked by the Earth
实际上是经过了大气层
actually slips through the atmosphere.
红光通过得最好
And the red light gets through the best.
阳光经过地球的大气层时
As the Sun's rays pass through the Earth's atmosphere,
会稍微有点弯曲
they are bent a little bit.
红光经过这样的弯曲 使得它越过
and the red rays are bent in such a way that they make it over the...
越过地球的表面照亮月球
over the surface of the Earth and illuminate the Moon.
只有红色或橙色的光
And when only red or orange light
到达月球的表面
reaches the lunar surface,
月球就呈现出红色
the Moon appears red,
另外一种光学现象平添了月球的神秘
another optical phenomenon that adds to the Moon's mystique.
那个神秘感部分
And part of that mystique
可以归因于月球戏剧性地出现在我们的上方
can be attributed to the dramatic presence of the Moon above us.
它在夜空中让其它的天体相形见绌
It outshines every other celestial body in the night sky.
月球有着特别的魔法
There's a special magic to the Moon,
它那变化着的月相
its changing phases,
在夜空中高挂闪亮
its brightness in a otherwise dark sky.
然而 我们也能在白天看到月亮
But we also see the Moon during the daytime.
这是什么原因？
Why is this?
其实很容易理解
It's actually very easy to understand
为什么能在白天看到月亮
why we can see the Moon during the daylight.
你可以在家里来示范一下
You can do this demonstration at home.
你所需要的就是将明亮的光源作为太阳
All you need is a bright light to act as the Sun
一只水果作为月球
and a piece of fruit to act as the Moon.
我的脸就作为地球
My face is acting as the Earth.
被照亮的部分是白天的部分
The lit-up side is the daylight side,
阴影部分是夜晚的部分
and the part in shadow is the nighttime side.
现在月球当然围绕着地球
Now, the Moon, of course, orbits the Earth,
在其运行的一个月里的某些时候
and at some of the times during the month in its orbit,
月球处在白昼的那一边
it's on the daylight side of the Moon.
所以我就能够在白天看到它
So I'm able to see it in full daylight.
事实上有许多行星和恒星
Actually, many planets and stars
只是在白天在我们的上空
are just above us during the daytime
但是太阳光确实是那么的明亮
but the light from the Sun is just so bright
让它们几乎看不出来
that it obscures nearly all of them.
只有月亮 它比最近的恒星亮10万倍
Only the Moon, which is 100,000 times brighter than the nearest star,
能透出来
shines through.
在白天我们不总是能看到月亮
We don't always see the Moon during the day
因为它不停地围绕着地球运转
because it's constantly moving around our Earth,
它不可能在每天的同一时间呆在同一个位置上
and it's not in the same position at the same time everyday.
不过在地球的某个地方 它始终能够被看到
But, somewhere on the planet, it's always visible.
然而 尽管已经有所认识 但并非月球的所有的东西
But as we learned, not everything about the Moon
都能够很容易得到解释或理解了
is easy to explain, or understand.
还有大量的问题尚未解决
There are still plenty of questions left unanswered.
自有记载的历史开始
It's been part of the Moon's mystique,
就一直存在着月球之谜
since history was first recorded.
我们永远紧贴着我们的邻居
We are forever tight to our neighbor,
但是 我们对关联却知之甚少
but we know so little about that dependence.
可能还有其它正在发生的情况
There could be other things that are happening
可是我们至今尚不知晓
that we just don't know about yet.
大约会在下个世纪
Over the next century or so,
我认为科学将带领我们进一步地弄明白它的奥秘
I think that science is going to...take us further into understanding its mysteries.
我们是否会完全认识它呢？ 我对此表示怀疑
Whether we will fully understand it? I doubt it.
当然我不认为认识了所有的东西
Certainly I don't think we know everything
就是认识了月球
there is to know about the Moon.
有大量的东西需要去认识
There is a tremendous amount to learn,
但是幸亏它在附近 我们在未来可进一步探索和了解它
but...fortunately it's within reach it and we will go exploring it at further and learn a lot more about it.
更彻底地探索月球世界之前
Until we will our efforts to explore the lunar world more thoroughly...
我们可能永远都不会知道所有秘密
we may never know all the secrets,
或希望解决隐藏的月球之谜
or hope to solve the hidden mysteries of the Moon.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing